Alpha Omicron Pi Records UA250
Digital Collections and Archives, Tufts University
Alpha Omicron Pi Records
circa 1908 -- 2017
Digital Collections and Archives, Tufts University
Alpha Omicron Pi
UA250
9.6 Linear Feet 8 record cartons
This collection contains the records of the Delta Chapter of Alpha Omicron Pi at Tufts University.
Conditions Governing Access
This collection is open for research.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Alpha Omicron Pi, 2018, accession UA-2018-062.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged in three series by format: To Dragma; Scrapbooks and bound volumes; and Administrative materials.
Biographical / Historical
The Delta chapter of Alpha Omicron Pi was established at Tufts University in 1908. The Delta chapter grew out of Alpha Delta Sigma, a local Greek letter society organized by six women (including founder Mary Grace Fickett, 1896) at Tufts in 1895. After association with other local societies in the New England area, Alpha Delta Sigma was formally initiated as the Delta chapter of Alpha Omicron Pi-- a national sorority founded in 1897—in the "wee small hours" of the morning of April 14, 1908. In the 1960s, members of the Delta chapter refused to participate in recruitment activities to protest the discriminatory recruitment rules of the Tufts Panhellenic Council; as a result, the chapter's charter was held in trust from 1969 until 1987, when the chapter was reestablished.
From 1987 through 2017, the Delta chapter held regular programs including recruitment and bid parties, philanthropy events, new member retreats, formal dances, and Big Sister Hunts. The chapter also participated in wider events and programming for Greek organizations at Tufts. The Delta chapter received the Tufts Mount Olympus Award—the award for Greek Chapter of the Year—numerous times between 1990 and 2017, and also received awards from Alpha Omicron Pi including the Academic Development Cup, the McCausland Cup, the Sheaf Performance Award, and awards for outstanding public relations and outstanding reporting. The motto of the Delta chapter was "strength through fellowship."
In September of 2016, a transgender student rushed the Delta chapter. After a delay in affirming the bid from Alpha Omicron Pi International, which oversees recruitment activities of all chapters, more than half of Delta's members left the sorority in October of 2016. The remaining members discussed leaving the national organization, but instead decided to push for a change in its policy on transgender students. On November 8, 2016, the Delta chapter issued a public statement regarding the chapter's division.
The efforts of the remaining members of the Delta chapter garnered the attention of Alpha Omicron Pi International; in 2015, the organization formed a Gender Identity Committee, which distributed an online survey to all chapters in order to gain a better understanding of how members viewed gender, and discuss possible changes to gender-identity policies. In 2017, the Alpha Omicron Pi International Diversity Policy and Bylaws were amended to add a non-discrimination clause for "other characteristics protected by state or federal law. Membership is open to women and those who identify as women." According to Delta chapter members, official fraternity documents were also amended to remove micro-aggressions in language, including terms such as "colonizing."
On December 11, 2017, the national Executive Board of Alpha Omicron Pi withdrew the Delta chapter's charter, citing "the chapter's inability to 'build their membership to sustain a viable AOII membership experience.'" Members were invited to affiliate with the Boston AOII Alumnae Chapter. In May of 2018, remaining residents moved out of the Delta chapter's sorority house at 25 Whitfield Road in Somerville.
Scope and Contents
This collection contains bound copies of To Dragma (translated as "the sheaf"), the official magazine of Alpha Omicron Pi; scrapbooks created by the members of the Tufts Delta Chapter; Alpha Omicron Pi songbooks; a yearbook published upon Alpha Omicron Pi's centennial in 1997; and administrative materials including awards received by the Delta Chapter, videos of events attended or held by the Delta Chapter, administrative notebooks, and new member materials.
Greek letter societies; Sororities; Student life; Student Activities -- Student Government, Clubs, and Organizations; Student life; Student activism
- To Dragma, circa 1908 -- 1993; UA250.001; 2.4 Linear Feet
  Arrangement
  This series is arranged in rough chronological order.
  Conditions Governing Access
  This series is open for research.
  Scope and Contents
  This series contains bound copies of To Dragma (translated as "the sheaf"), the official magazine of Alpha Omicron Pi. This series also contains a binder of photocopied issues of To Dragma, as well as a document titled "Historical Notes on Women at Tufts and AOPi."
  - To Dragma and historical material, circa 1908 -- 1993; UA250.001.001; 1.2 Linear Feet (Box 1-2, 12, 14, 15-16, Box 1)
    This file contains bound copies of To Dragma from 1909-1939; as well as a binder containing photocopied issues of To Dragma from c. 1908-1993, and a document titled "Historical Notes on Women at Tufts and AOPi."
  - To Dragma, circa 1940 -- 1965; UA250.001.002; 1.2 Linear Feet (Box 1-2, 12, 14, 15-16, Box 2)
    This file contains bound copies of To Dragma from c. 1940-1965.
- Scrapbooks and bound volumes, circa 1931 -- 2015; UA250.002; 6 Linear Feet
  This series contains scrapbooks created by the members of the Alpha Omicron Pi Delta Chapter from c. 1988-2015; Alpha Omicron Pi songbooks from 1931, 1971, and 1989; and a yearbook published upon Alpha Omicron Pi's centennial in 1997 titled, "Celebrate the Century: The Centennial History of Alpha Omicron Pi 1897-1997."
  - Scrapbooks, circa 1988 -- 1992; UA250.002.003; 1.2 Linear Feet (Box 3-8, Box 3)
  - Scrapbooks, circa 1993 -- 1995; UA250.002.004; 1.2 Linear Feet (Box 3-8, Box 4)
  - Scrapbooks, circa 1996 -- 2001; UA250.002.005; 1.2 Linear Feet (Box 3-8, Box 5)
    Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
    Some items in this file may be fragile and require supervision while in use. Please contact DCA for details.
  - Scrapbooks, circa 2002 -- 2012; UA250.002.006; 1.2 Linear Feet (Box 3-8, Box 6)
  - Scrapbooks, songbooks, centennial yearbook, circa 1931 -- 2015; UA250.002.007; 1.2 Linear Feet (Box 3-8, Box 7)
    This file contains scrapbooks from c. 2013-2015; songbooks from 1931, 1971, and 1989; and a yearbook published upon Alpha Omicron Pi's centennial in 1997 titled, "Celebrate the Century: The Centennial History of Alpha Omicron Pi 1897-1997."
- Administrative materials, circa 1950 -- 2017; UA250.003; 1.2 Linear Feet
  This series is arranged by format.
  This series contains awards received by the Delta Chapter in paper, plaque, and other forms; videos of events attended or held by the Delta Chapter; and administrative materials including a President's notebook, a PR notebook with clippings from the Tufts Daily, and new member materials.
  - Awards, videos, and administrative materials, circa 1950 -- 2017; UA250.003.008; 1.2 Linear Feet (Box 3-8, Box 8)
    This file contains awards received by the Delta Chapter in paper, plaque, and other forms; videos of events attended or held by the Delta Chapter; and administrative materials including a President's notebook, a PR notebook with clippings from the Tufts Daily, and new member materials.